Guide to the Seymour Melman Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Seymour Melman Papers,
1958-1997
Melman, Seymour.
46 linear ft. (ca. 16,400 items in 146 boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library,
4079724
Biographical Note
Author and professor of industrial engineering at Columbia University. Prof. Melman was born in 1917.
Scope and Content
Manuscripts, notes, conference papers, and printed materials. Included are research files, notes, and other materials used for manuscripts of THE IMPACT OF THE PATENT SYSTEM ON RESEARCH (1958), Study of the Subcommittee on Patents, Trademarks, and Copyrights of the Committee of the Judiciary United States Senate, 85th Congress, 2nd Session Persuant to S. Res. 236, Study No. 11; OUR DEPLETED SOCIETY (1965); PENTAGON CAPITALISM (1970); THE PERMANENT WAR ECONOMY (1974); PROFITS WITHOUT PRODUCTION (1983). The development of a military industry and federal policy in the U.S. is recorded in THE MILITARY ECONOMY (1981), a 2 volume, unpublished collection of New York Times articles that traces war economy from 1865 to 1981. THE PEACE RACE (1962) research papers record the national debate on military policy under President Kennedy. The research papers for IN THE NAME OF AMERICA (1968) report violations of the laws of war by the U.S. in Vietnam. There are also conference papers and related materials documenting efforts to implement demilitarization and economic conversion.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 2 series:
Series I: Book Titles
Series II: "Research Conference on Disarmament"
Subjects
United States--Armed Forces--Procurement.; United States--Economic conditions--1947-; Defense contracts--United States.; Disarmament--Economic aspects--United States.; Industrial engineering.; Industrial management--United States.; Industrial policy--United States.; Industrial productivity--United States.; Industries--United States.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Atrocities.; War--Economic aspects--United States.; War crimes.; Articles.; Brochures.; First drafts.; Manuscripts for publication.; Notes.; Papers.; Prefaces.; Authors, American.; College teachers.; Engineers--United States.; Industrial engineers--United States.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
Papers Melman, Seymour Gifts, 1962, 1970, 1974, 1983, 1997
10/01/1997 97/98-4 Research materials Prof. Melman Gift
Gift of Prof. Melman, 1962, 1970, 1974, 1983, & 1997.
- Series I: Book Titles
  Includes manuscripts and research files.
  - Subseries I.1: Civil Defense Against Nuclear Attack
    - Pamphlets, reprints, clippings, etc. (Box 1)
  - Subseries I.2: Disarmament
    - Clippings, reprints, notes, from First Intercollegiate Conference on Disarmament and Arms Control, Swarthmore College, 1962, (Pamphlets and notes) (Box 2, 3, 4)
      [from first congressional hearings, conference papers on disarmament and inspection; papers from the Mershon National Security Program, Ohio State University, 1959]
  - Subseries I.3: In the Name of America
    - Research papers (Box 5, 6, 7, 8)
    - Research papers; paperback copy of book (Box 9)
  - Subseries I.4: Pentagon Capitalism
    - Research material (Box 10)
    - Chapter 2: Research material (Box 10, 11)
    - Chapter 3: Research material (Box 12, 13)
    - Chapter 4: Research material (Box 13, 14, 15)
    - Chapter 5: Research material (Box 15, 16, 17)
    - Chapters 6: Research material (Box 17)
    - Chapter 7: Research material (Box 17)
    - Chapter 8: Research material (Box 18)
    - Chapter 9: Research material (Box 19)
    - Manuscript--first draft; printed copy (Box 20)
  - Subseries I.5: Our Depleted Society
    - Research material (Box 21)
    - Chapter 2: Research material (Box 21)
    - Chapter 3: Research material (Box 22)
    - Chapter 4: Research material (Box 23, 24)
    - Chapter 5: Research material (Box 24, 25, 26)
    - Chapters 6-8: Research material (Box 26)
    - Chapter 9: Research material (Box 26, 27)
    - Chapter 10: Research material (Box 27)
    - Chapters 11-12: Research material (Box 28)
    - Chapter 13: Research material (Box 28, 29)
    - Chapters 14-15: Research material (Box 29)
    - Manuscript final draft; printed copy of book (Box 30)
  - Subseries I.6: The Peace Race
    - Chapters 1-8: Research material (Box 31)
      [Marked by Melman as unused material]
    - Chapters 9-13: Research material (Box 32)
    - Chapters 1-7: Research material (Box 33)
    - Chapters 8-13: Research material; printed copy of book (Box 34)
  - Subseries I.7: The Military Economy
    - Part 1 A collection of articles in the New York Times from the Civil War to 1981, with an introduction, "The Transformation of War Economy", by Melman (Box 34)
    - Parts 2-5 (Box 35)
  - Subseries I.8: Permanent War Economy
    - Research notes and material (Box 36)
    - Chapter 2: Research notes and material (Box 37, 38)
    - Chapter 3: Research notes and material (Box 38)
    - Chapter 4: Research notes and material (Box 39, 40, 42, 43)
    - Chapter 4: Research notes and material (Box 40, 41)
    - Chapter 5: Research notes and material (Box 43, 44, 46, 47)
    - Chapter 5: Research notes and material (Box 44, 45)
    - Chapter 6: Research notes and material (Box 47, 48)
    - Chapter 7: Research notes and material (Box 49, 50)
    - Chapter 7: Research notes and material (Box 50, 51)
    - Chapter 8: Research notes and material (Box 51-53)
    - Chapter 9: Research notes and material (Box 53, 54)
    - Chapter 10: Research notes and material (Box 56)
    - Chapter 10: Research notes and material (Box 55, 56)
  - Subseries I.9: Inspection for Disarmament
    - Misc. data, correspondence, papers, drafts 1 & 2 (Box 57, 58)
  - Subseries I.10: Profits Without Production
    - Prologue: Research material (Box 59, 60, 77)
    - Chapter 1: Research material (Box 61, 62, 77)
    - Chapter 2Research material (Box 63, 77)
    - Chapter 3-4: Research material (Box 63, 78)
    - Chapter 5: Research material (Box 63, 79)
    - Chapter 6: Research material (Box 64, 65, 80)
      [Some material marked by Melman as unused]
    - Chapter 7: Research material (Box 81)
    - Chapter 8: Research material (Box 81, 82)
    - Chapter 9: Research material (Box 66, 67, 83)
    - Chapter 10: Research material (Box 68, 69, 84, 85, 86, 87)
      [Some material in Box 68 marked by Melman as unused]
    - Chapter 11: Research material (Box 70, 71, 88)
      [Some material in Box 71 marked by Melman as unused]
    - Chapter 12: Research material (Box 72, 90, 91, 92, 93, 94)
      [Some material in Box 72 marked by melman as unused]
    - Chapter 13: Research material (Box 73)
    - Chapter 14: Research material (Box 74, 75, 95, 96, 97)
      [Some material in Box 74 marked by Melman as unused]
    - Chapter 15: Research material (Box 76)
      [Marked by Melmas as unused]
  - Subseries I.11: The Impact of the Patent System on Research
    - Manuscript (Box 98)
  - Subseries I.12: The Production of Technical Knowledge in Relation to the Patent System
    - Research notes, 1956 (Box 98)
  - Subseries I.13: Conversion and Reindustrialization: Alternatives to Pentagon Indsutrial Policy
    - Conference paper, 13 June 1987 (Box 98)
  - Subseries I.14: Managerial vs. Cooperative Decision Making in Israel
    - Manuscript, 1970 (Box 99)
  - Subseries I.15: The National Priorities Problem: Choices and Consequences
    - Conference papers, September 30-October 1, 1966 (Box 99)
  - Subseries I.16: After Capitalism: From Managerialism to Workplace Democracy
    - Introduction: Managerialism and "The Market" are not Forever (Box 100)
    - Part I: From Feudalism to Capitalism, and After Chapter I: The Shape of Production Under State Capitalism (Box 100)
    - Chapter 2: The Founding Alienation of Capitalism (Box 101)
    - Part II: State & Corporate Managers Impose Alienation on a Whole Society by Destroying Production Capacity Chapter 3: Alienation from Accumulation Makes the U.S. a Third Rare Economy (Box 101-108)
    - Chapter 4: State Managers Accumulate Military Power Without Limit (Box 108 & 109)
    - Chapter 5: Hidden Costs of Campaigning for World Hegemony (Box 109 - 115)
    - Chapter 6: The Lesson of Soviet Russia: From Alienation to Production Collapse (Box 116 - 118)
    - Part III: Managing as Deindustrialization Proceeds Chapter 7: Managers Use Hi-Tech in an Attempt to Make Workers and Unions Obsolete (Box 119 - 122)
    - Chapter 8: Management Promotes Ownership Without Control (Box 120 - 125)
    - Part IV: Workers Create a Process of Disalienated Decision-Making for an Economy and Society After Capitalism Chapter 9: Creating Workplace Democracy (Box 125 - 128)
    - Chapter 10: Disalienation by Design: Installing Workplace Democracy (Box 128 - 140)
    - Chapter 11: White Collar Joins The Blue (Box 140 - 143)
    - Part V: Advancing Workplace Democracy Chapter 12: The Advancing Process of Capitalism and Workplace Democracy (Box 144)
    - Conclusion: An Exit Path from Capitalism to Workplace Democracy (Box 145)
    - Appendices: I: Selected Bibliography on Workplace Democracy (Box 145)
- Series II: "Research Conference on Disarmament"
  A large bound volume containing the original papers delivered at the Conference.
  - Includes papers by: David F. Cavers -- Samuel Lubell -- Herbert Ritvo -- Charles O. Porter -- Robert W. Kastenmeier -- Christopher Hohenemser -- Arthur I. Waskow -- Robert Engler -- Alberta B. Szalita -- Lewis C. Bohn -- Leonard S. Rodberg -- John Martinson & C. W. Churchman -- Amitai Etzioni -- J. David Singer -- Roger Fisher -- Emile Benoit -- John P. Hardt -- Richard C. Raymond -- John E. Ullmann -- Richard L. Meier, Columbia University, 1 & 2 December 1961, (1 volume) (Box 146)
    [Gift of Professor Melman, 8 August 2002]